Super excited for this
module on SQL query tuning.
Almost everything we've done in
this class up until this point
is based on logical query tuning
where we type in the code and
the database engine determines
the most efficient way to run.
In this particular module, we'll start to
look under the hood at
the physical components
of SQL and identify areas where
performance is lagging and look
at ways to improve that performance.
And so first thing we'll
do is understand what a query
tuning plan is, looking at estimated
primarily in actual execution
plans to see how the code runs.
Probably 40, 50 hours of the been
gone training I've been to is
focused on query tuning. The other
thing I noticed is whenever I go to
a database conference and these
professionals in the field 20 years
plus want to examine code more
deeply, they'll typically just ask the
presenter, can you show me the
estimated plan? So they're looking
at the query tuning plan as kind of
the highest level of understanding
the code being run. We'll identify
some obvious areas for what
makes a query running slow, and then
we'll follow up with understanding
indexes, how we can create and
change indexes to improve. You're
probably too young to remember this
commercial, and I'll just a portion
of it but as we go through the
material on query tuning we'll
show two different types of code
options and so it just reminds me of
this Kia commercial where these
mice are indicating that you could
deal with this particular car you
can deal with that particular car
and in our case we'll be looking
at one particular set of code and
another set of code to see which
one would run more efficiently okay
so let's take a look at what we'll
be doing the whole idea of query
tuning is to figure out how to make
the code run more efficiently and to
identify areas where the code runs
slowly and try to fix those mistakes.
We'll also focus on how SQL retrieves
the data and not just the data
that returns. So how does it
physically go into the storage to grab
information and to provide that
information back? And so we're looking at
the ultimate goal of getting faster
results and in more efficient code.
All right so this starts us
with if you watch that original
video I think this was the first
item here but we'll begin with
different types of structure
within the database and so on the
screen here you can see this
symbol here is representative
of a database and on the right
side is simply how this data are
stored in each one of these
squares, if you think of a page,
just a single page,
typical page in a notebook,
SQL Server is physically stored
in pages. And these pages,
of course, have a little
bit of metadata headers and
footers and different ways to
go from one page to another.
But effectively, the information
are contained on different pages.
And the first type of organization
that we can have is a heap.
And the idea of a heap is that
it simply has no structure at
all. So when data are added
into the database, it's just
simply added into the next
available page within the data set.
Now, one thing I got confused of in
the training is sometimes Bingham
would talk about heaps are
beneficial, and sometimes they're not
beneficial. For most of our
discussion here today, we'll consider
a heap to be slow in terms of
writing logical queries against the
code. So our typically select
statements, we don't necessarily want
to have a heap. That said, the
advantage of a heap, at least from
our perspective today, is just
one. That is if you're importing
massive data. So if you're doing a
bulk import into a database, it is
more efficient to use a heap because
it doesn't have to organize it
as much as when we do our other
type of database storage options.
So if you think of a heap, it's
just kind of like this big basket.
We it lands, that's where it's going to
be. There's no necessary organization.
If you think about a phone book,
we'll use that analogy when we
get to the next item. But if you
think about a phone book that's
not organized in any way, it's
just you simply start going page
by page trying to find somebody's
last name. But there's no order
to it, no alphabetical order to
it. It'd become very difficult to
manage accessing data. But in
terms of putting data in, it would
be very easy. You can just throw
stuff in at the end or wherever
there's an open spot. And that's
what makes heaps efficient for
importing data, and that's about
the effectiveness of the heap.
So here's a simple table, something
you would have created in the
intro class. We're just going to
create a table called pet, and
we give it two different columns,
and then we're going to insert
some data into the pet database.
But you'll see in this particular
case, we don't have a primary
key established. and one of the
few query tuning items that we
learned about in the intro class was
when you create a primary key,
it'll automatically create a
clustered index. And we haven't
quite gotten to clustered index here,
but without having a primary key,
the most basic form of storage
would be a heap. And so as an
example, let me run this code and
we've created our data set. And
now I can select a new query let
me in fact here I'm going to say
we have a pet ID so we've created
this pet ID you can see the information
three two four one it's just
throwing the information as we
typed it and so if I go back to how
we put this information in you can
see three two four one it's just
a heap we're just throwing it into
the heap and how we can tell it's
a heap and we'll use this estimated
plan, this button right here.
So if you look at the
execute and you go a
couple to the right, we
have our execution plan.
And when I execute this plan,
as we're reading a query plan,
this would be the most basic,
you typically read it from
right to left. So in this
case, we're doing a table scan.
And if you put your mouse over
the top, it gives you all the
information in terms of how many
rows will be executed, how long it
expects it to execute and what
type of physical operation. So here
we're doing a table scan and that
table scan takes up all the cost
and table scan in this instance
would indicate that we have a
heap and it's scanning the entire
table in order to find pet ID
from pet. And so there's no
efficiency by creating that clustered
index. If we only have a heap, we
have no primary key established.
So let's go back to our slides
and go to the next option.
And what we did just now doing
select pet ID from pet, it did
a table scan. And so effectively,
in order to find information,
it would have to scan
through every page in order
to find the information
that we're looking for.
So the next item, the
more efficient one, and as
a reminder, when you
create a primary key in SQL
Server, it automatically
creates a clustered index.
And that clustered index will
create a B-tree format. And I think
you'll cover B-tree in a lot more
detail in Dr. Kim's class. But
a B-tree effectively will give
you an organization or a roadmap.
And so if you think
here of a phone book and
maybe this particular
page covers A through C.
So anything that is to the
left of, for instance, B might
show up over here. Anything
after B, B, and C would occur
over here. And so you can see
it's much more efficient in order
to go and to find different
information in the database.
Now, if you do a clustered
index based on that primary key,
that clustered index would
be on, in this case, pet ID.
And so if I go back into SQL Server,
and I have the code here, and in
this code, we create a primary
key, which we typically have done,
right? we've always created a primary
key but we create a primary key
on pet ID and we just called this
a little bit different name pet
with primary key and run this code
it's showing we already have one we
delete that okay
so now we'll run this
code and remember when we
ran this code it was three
two four one but now if
we create a new query
indicate select pet ID from
pet with PK it's interesting
it now has an order because
it's stored it in the
data set with order now in
the clustered index and now
if we go this is kind of an
aha moment. We find the
query tuning. We click on it.
And now instead of doing a non-clustered
scan, we're now doing
a clustered index scan.
Let's go over to slides
and learn more about that.
So we've moved from a heap, a non
-clustered index. Now we have a
clustered index. But in this case,
you can see we're still doing a
scan of the entire table. So in
our scan, we're reading the entire
table and the problem is we don't
have a where clause in order to
allow us to quickly go to the
particular page that would have that
information and so sometimes you
might think that more code is
not as good so for instance if I
come here and I type in where say
pet ID is equal to 2 we've added
some predicate logic but now
that we have the predicate logic
and you think about a clustered
index, it will know where that
pet ID 2 is equal to, thinking
of a phone book that has a
particular order alphabetized.
And in this particular case,
think of the alphabetized as just
a pet ID, so numbers one through
however many pets we have.
And so now if we run this code, we
get the item that we want. But more
importantly, if we go to our query
plan, we can see now it does a
clustered index seek instead of a
clustered index scan and if you look
on the information with your mouse
over the top of it you can see the
number of executions one the number
of rows to be read one and when
we had our scan versus to seek it
would read the total number of rows
in the entire data set so we had
four rows so it should read four
but in this case it only reads one
so let me quickly jump over here and
show you well for instance this
information it's doing a table scan
and when we put the mouse over the
top you can see it's going to run
for number of rows for all X because
I wrote run all four rows so if
we had a million rows it would run
all million so one of the first
takeaways is anytime that you can
have a clustered index and you can do
a where clause based or predicate
logic based on that clustered index
then that will allow you to do a
clustered index seek instead of a
clustered index scan meaning it will
run much more efficiently in terms
of this one runs right to the item
itself so if we have a clustered
index scan it's still scanning every
row with the clustered index seek
it can use the B tree so it could
it could start here decide whether
to go to the left or right of the
B tree and quickly execute and find
the information that it's looking
for with a clustered index seek.
Okay, so up until now, we have a
heap, which is an unorganized, non
-clustered index. We don't have a
clustered index. We must not have a
primary key, or we didn't add the
constraint to add a clustered index.
In that case, it will
always do a table scan.
It's good for importing
data, but for now, let's say
that's it. It's only good
for importing both data.
And then we can create a
clustered index. Now, if
we do a clustered index and
we don't use the predicate
logic, the where clause,
it will also do a scan.
So it's still inefficient,
although the data are organized.
And if we use the where clause
on a clustered index, you can
see where we do the clustered
index seek. And this would,
anytime we can have a
clustered index seek, we
know we're working with
very efficient code.
So in terms of good, bad, and
indifferent, let's argue clustered
index seek is the best when we
want to directly and efficiently
find the information, particularly
using the predicate logic.
and you can see here predicate
logic that starts with the
clustering key simply means that
the predicate logic is using the
cluster key whatever we determine
to be the primary key or
later we can create some other
types of index not clustered index
but non-clustered index and
we'll get to that in just a bit.